Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project, 593058
  - Cappoletti, Caroline Lavecchia, 1973 April 28; 593197 (Box 88, Reel 856a, Box 1, Folder 8)
    This interview was conducted on April 28, 1973 by Joan Granucci at an unspecified location. The interview covers Caroline Lavecchia Cappeletti's childhood in Italy, her parents' immigration to the United States (US), her marriage, her extended family, and her social life. Cappeletti discusses her childhood, including her parents' immigration to the US; her life in Italy with her grandfather; and her immigration to the US after his death. She describes being introduced to her husband and having to meet him secretly because of the strict rules her father set for her behavior. She describes the buildings and people in the West Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York, including the fact that few Italians lived there. She discusses her work in a dress factory; modeling dress samples while the manager altered them; and sewing buttons by hand and other pieces on sewing machines. She also discusses her salary and the fact that the factory was not unionized. She describes her living situation after her marriage: she and her husband lived with his four brothers and their wives, and the group bought two apartment houses. She discusses financial difficulties they had and the fact that all of the women had to work in order for the group to afford the mortgage payments on the buildings. She discusses her social life before and during her marriage, including taking boat trips along the Hudson River and dancing at the Roseland Ballroom.
    See also: Life Before Immigration or Migration, and Unionization.
    A transcript and index are available for this interview. An electronic transcript of this interview is also available by request.
  - Caravello, [Unknown] and Lindsey Gaetana, 1973 May 4; 592016
    Mr. Caravello was born in Italy and was one of five children. He attended high school and worked in a vineyard with his father and one of his brothers. He immigrated to the United States when he was 19 years old. He lived in New York, New York and Madison, Wisconsin. In New York he worked in a nickel-plating factory. He married and had at least one child.
    The first minute of this recording contains the beginning of an interview with Lindsey Gaetana who explains that he was born in Palermo, Italy in 1885 and immigrated to the United States (US) in 1905. The rest of the recording contains the interview with Mr. Caravello.
    This interview was conducted by Bau Morrow at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York on May 4, 1973. The first name of the narrator is unknown. Mr. Caravello is sometimes hard to understand due to his Italian accent. The interview covers his working life in Italy and the United States (US). Caravello discusses working with his father and older brother in a vineyard in Italy and grafting vines from France onto native vines. He explains that a disease killed off the majority of the vines before his immigration to the US, but does not say whether this led to his decision to immigrate. He explains that his father was the foreman of the vineyard; that a director and inspector would come from Rome every two weeks to oversee their work; and that they arranged for Caravello to attend high school. He recounts his achievements in school proudly. He discusses the fact that he immigrated to the US in order to work in vineyards in California but that his family and a good job in a nickel-plating factory kept him in New York City. He recounts moving with his wife and baby to Madison, Wisconsin after five or six years in New York and working as a machinist.
    Other topics include the nursing home at which Caravello lived at the time of the interview and the care he received; his mother's sense of style; and his siblings' lives after his immigration.
    Vineyards |z Italy.
  - Chinoy, Belle, 1975 February 25; 593200 (Box 88, Reel 859a, Box 1, Folder 9)
    Belle Chinoy was born in Russia. She lived in Saint Petersburg before immigrating to the United States. She worked as a draper in the garment industry in New York, New York before her marriage. She was a member of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. She married and had two sons and one daughter. Her husband worked as a paperhanger and a painter. They owned a grocery store in Manhattan and a vegetable store in Newark, New Jersey.
    This interview was conducted by Louise Mayo at the Daughters of Israel nursing home in West Orange, New Jersey on February 25, 1975. The interview covers Belle Chinoy's early life in Russia, her working life in the United States, and her family. Chinoy discusses her early life in Saint Petersburg, Russia, including anti-Jewish laws that dispossessed her father of his property and the dispersal of her and her siblings to different family members in Saint Petersburg. She describes different jobs she held in the garment industry in New York, New York, including operator and draper; her salary as a piece worker; the difference in salaries between union and non-union factories; the ethnic demographics of the garment workers; and the division of jobs between men and women. Other topics include her living arrangements before her marriage; her continuation of her education at night school; the fact that she learned Yiddish in the garment factories; and her husband's occupations, which included painter and paperhanger.
    A summary is available for this interview.
  - Christianson, Victor, 1973 April 5; 593202 (Box 88, Reel 861a - 861b, Box 1, Folder 10)
    Victor Christianson was born in 1884 in an unspecified European country (likely Denmark). He and his parents immigrated to the United States in 1885. He was an only child. He graduated from high school and trained as an electrician. He worked at the American Smelting and Refining Company in Perth Amboy, New Jersey and with Thomas Edison in his laboratory in Orange, New Jersey. He moved to New York and attended classes at the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn and Stewart's Automobile School on 57th Street in Manhattan. He owned an automotive repair shop. He married around 1921 and had one son.
    This interview was conducted by Mary B. Alexander at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York. The date of the interview is unknown. The interview covers Victor Christianson's childhood in Perth Amboy, New Jersey; his working life as an electrician and automotive repairman; and his family. Christianson discusses his childhood; his parents; and the ethnic demographics of Perth Amboy. He recounts working as an electrician for the American Smelting and Refining Company in Perth Amboy; with Thomas Edison in his experimental laboratory in Orange, New Jersey; and his decision to move to New York in order to gain better opportunities. He recounts his interest in cars, including driving a car for the first time in 1906; learning automotive repair at Stewart's Automobile School on 57th Street in Manhattan; and opening his own repair shop in the Washington Heights neighborhood of Manhattan. He discusses his family, including his unhappiness about his estrangement from his son; his wife's health; and the deaths of his parents. Other topics include his opposition to unions; his opinions on politics; and a visit to Copenhagen, Denmark with his mother when he was six years old.
    An index is available for this interview.
    Electricians |z New York (State) |z New York.; Family life issues.
  - Cinisomo, Mario, 1973 April 4 and Undated; 344041 (Box 11, Reel 32a, Box 12, Reel 32b - 32d, Box 101, Box 1, Folder 11)
    Mario Cinisomo was born in 1913 in Brooklyn, New York to Italian immigrants. He worked as a longshoreman from 1932 until his retirement. He was a member of the International Longshoremen's Association Local 1814, and held the position of Secretary-Treasurer at the time of the interview.
    One interview with Mario Cinisomo was conducted by Frank Farragaso at the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA) Union Hall on Court Street in Brooklyn, New York. The date of the interview is unknown. A second interview was conducted by Leon Fink at the International Longshoremen's Association Union Hall on Court Street in Brooklyn, New York on April 4, 1973. The main topics of these interviews include the lives of Cinisomo's parents; his employment prior to his involvement with the International Longshoremen's Association (ILA) Local 1814; social issues within the ILA; and social activities in which he participated outside of the ILA. Cinisomo discusses his father, including his positions as sergeant major in the Italian Navy and as a sailor on a Swedish merchant marine ship, and difficulties he had while working in the US due to his height, health issues, and illiteracy. He discusses his mother being a housewife; her work assisting other Italian immigrants in the United States (US) with their paperwork; and his parents' arranged marriage in Italy. Cinisomo discusses his educational experiences, including graduating from public school; attending high school at night; and taking some college classes sponsored by the Works Progress Administration (WPA). He describes his employment before the ILA, including working in a laundry, a paper box factory, and as a grocery clerk, and his employment as an organizer in the WPA from the early 1930s until the start of World War II. He recalls social issues within the ILA, including the fact that the Irish and Germans controlled the union; that Italian workers were confined to working in the holds of the ships; and that striking was difficult because the Irish controlled the ILA and the police department. Cinisomo discusses leisure activities in which he participated, including attending church every Sunday; playing cards on his days off; and not playing sports because he was exhausted after his shifts. Index is available for the April 4th interview.
    See also: Canossa, Bruno; Ferrentino, Rosario and Mario Cinisomo; and Passage.
  - Clanton, Elizabeth, 1975 October 24; 344042 (Box 101, Cd ref33, ref33a, Box 12, Reel 33a - 33b, Box 13, Reel 33c - 33e)
    Elizabeth Clanton was born in Atmore, Alabama in 1901. Her grandparents were freed slaves and her father was a laborer on the railroad and in a saw mill. She married in 1920, had two sons, divorced, and remarried later in life. She worked in Illinois, Ohio, and California, before moving to New York, New York, where she worked as a nurses' aid and was a member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union.
    This interview was conducted by Leon Fink on October 24, 1975 at Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York. This interview covers Elizabeth Clanton's childhood in Alabama; her migration throughout the United States (US); her work as a nurses' aide; and her union activity. She begins by describing her childhood in Atmore, Alabama. She focuses on how Atmore was divided along racial lines, describing segregation in neighborhoods, schools, churches, and the movies; and the limited, strained social contact between members of the white and black communities. She also describes learning how to read in school, which enabled her to read the newspaper for her parents, neither of whom were literate. Other topics from her childhood include her close relationship with her father; some of her grandparents' history; leisure activities; holiday traditions; the type of music to which she listened; and her religious traditions and values.
    Clanton explains that it was typical for parents to decide who was an appropriate match for their daughters and describes the strict rules that governed interactions between young men and women. She describes meeting and marrying her first husband in Alabama despite her family's reservations about her being too young and her occupation as a domestic worker for various families in Atmore, a position that she acquired from her mother when the latter became ill. She spends a great deal of time discussing her movement throughout the US, including moving to Cleveland, Ohio in order to find domestic work to support her children, whom she had left with her parents after she separated from her husband; receiving a certificate in practical nursing in Chicago, Illinois; and moving to Brooklyn, New York to live with one of her sons. She recalls sending much of the money she earned back to her family and writing letters to her mother and children to accompany each paycheck. Clanton discusses her union involvement, including being introduced to the idea of unions by organizer Jesse Olson while working at Beth Israel Hospital, as a nurses' aide, in Manhattan; going to various hotels in New York City for union meetings; discussing union activities with co-workers only on breaks or after work; and participating in a hospital workers' strike in 1959. Clanton discusses her opinion that despite the union not supporting striking workers sufficiently she realized the benefits of belonging to a union; her appreciation of Local 1199 after her retirement; and the educational programs and social activities that Local 1199 provided.
    African Americans -- Relations with Jews.; Cleveland (Ohio) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century.
  - Cohen, Arthur, 1973 April 27; 593137 (Box 79, Reel 791a, Box 80, Reel 791b, Box 1, Folder 12)
    Arthur Cohen was born in New York, New York around 1886 and was the youngest of seven sons. His father was a butcher on Hamilton Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. The family moved to the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan in 1891. Cohen attended the Hebrew Technical Institute and graduated as an electrician's helper.
    This interview was conducted by Edmund Lake on April 27, 1973 at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York. It covers Arthur Cohen's childhood, his work as an electrician, and his career as a semi-professional baseball player. Cohen discusses growing up in a predominantly Irish section of the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, in which his family was one of two Jewish families, and how his mother would be protected on her way home from local poker games by neighborhood ruffians. He describes his work at the Herring-Hall-Marvin Safe Company, attaching safe doors and setting the combinations. He describes his work as an electrician for industrial companies and being forced to leave this work due to his wife's illness. He recounts his years playing baseball as a catcher and traveling with two teams, the Colonials and the Chambers Arrows.
    Transcript, index, and subject cards are available for this interview.
    Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Ethnic relations.; Semi-professional baseball |z New York (State); Electricians |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Cohen, Rose, 1973 March 30; 593139 (Box 101, Cd 9, Box 80, Reel 793a - 793b, Box 1, Folder 13)
    Rose Cohen was born in Russia and was one of six children. She immigrated to the United States in 1912, where she worked in the garment industry. She was a member of the Socialist Party of America, the Workmen's Circle, and an unspecified labor union (likely the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union).
    This interview was conducted by Wendy Fisher on March 30, 1973 at an unspecified location. The interview covers Rose Cohen's early life and education in Russia, her immigration to the United States (US), her political activity, her working life, and her union activity. Cohen discusses her childhood in Russia, in particular, convincing her father to allow her to attend public school. She discusses immigrating to the US and living with her sisters on Orchard Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She discusses her first job in a shirtwaist factory; her attempts at unionizing the shop; and her attempts at recruiting workers into the Socialist Party of America. Other topics include brief histories of the Russian Revolution and the Workmen's Circle and the importance of socialism in Cohen's life.
    Women socialists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.
  - Coker, Cora, 1974 April 25; 344045 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    Cora Coker was born in Hammond, Louisiana in 1904 and was one of eight children. Her father was a railroad worker. She attended school in both Hammond and Chicago, Illinois, where she graduated from eighth grade and attended a pre-vocational training program at Wendell Phillips Academy High School. She worked in domestic service in New York and in factories in Chicago, where she sewed and made box springs and cushions. She lived in the Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York before settling in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan after her marriage. She had four children. She organized the Harlem Mothers Community Club.
    This interview was conducted by Cenen Moreno at the A. Philip Randolph Houses in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York on April 25, 1974. The audio recording for this interview is missing. This interview covers Cora Coker's childhood in Louisiana and Illinois; her migration to New York, New York; her jobs in domestic service and in factories; and her family. Coker recounts her childhood in Hammond, Louisiana, noting that strawberry picking season interfered with her education. She recalls Klu Klux Klan activity in her city; that white people owned many of the farms and businesses in the area; and the lynching of a woman named Emma Hooker. She explains that her family generally had friendly relationships with white people, recalling that they lived on property owned by white people before her father built her family a house; that many people in her family were named after the family that owned the property on which they lived; and that that family sent them a wagon full of toys at Christmas. She explains that her family moved from Hammond to Chicago, Illinois after her father lost his job for walking through a segregated railroad station and then fighting with the man who chastised him for it. She compares Hammond and Chicago, noting that her neighborhood in Chicago was split between black residents and Polish residents but that there was no animosity between the groups. She explains that she quit school because she saw no future in it.
    Coker explains that she migrated to New York, New York and settled in the Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York with her fiance's friends. She describes her husband's occupation as a boxer and notes that, although he excelled in his sport, there were few chances for him to fight in big matches because of discrimination against black contenders. She explains that she found various domestic worker positions through an employment agency and that she worked less frequently after having children. She recalls a contrast between being content and in love and struggling to make ends meet during the Great Depression. She describes the differences between her relationship with her mother and her children's relationship with her, focusing on her efforts to communicate with them, including having monthly family meetings. Other topics include her leisure activities and traditions; her father's occupation and income; her husband's death in 1943; her children's education and occupations; and a comparison between life in the northern United States (US) and the southern US.
    Summary is available for this interview.
  - Cole, Annie, 1975 November 13; 344046 (Box 101, Cd ref37)
    Annie Cole was born in Forest Home, Alabama on January 25, 1924. She graduated from the Tuskegee Institute with an associate degree in dietary health. She migrated to New York, New York and worked at Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx. She was a member of Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union.
    This interview was conducted by Sasha Silverstein on November 13, 1975 at Local 1199 Drug, Hospital, and Health Care Employees Union in Manhattan, New York. Topics of discussion include Annie Cole's childhood, education, work experience, and union involvement. Cole briefly discusses her early life in Alabama and Texas; her education at the Tuskegee Institute; and the hardships she endured in attending college, including working long hours during the day and being too tired to study at night. She spends a majority of the interview discussing her working life, including a 6 month internship at an unspecified hospital on 125th street in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and her job as a dietary aide at Montefiore Hospital in the Bronx, New York, which she began in 1952. She discusses in detail her reasons for joining Local 1199, including speaking with a strike organizer about her frustrations regarding taking on the work of the striking workers, in addition to her own. Cole discusses issues that she faced once she was a member of the union, including not receiving the same pay as hospital employees with different job titles, even though they did the same work, and unfair scheduling and benefits. She also discusses her struggles against management regarding workplace and pay discrimination throughout her career.
  - Council Workshop for Senior Citizens I, 1973 March 29; 344223 (Box 72, Reel 215a, Box 73, Reel 215b)
    This group interview was conducted by student interviewers, Edmund Lake and Ron Walker, and an unknown moderator on March 29, 1973. This interview contains a roundtable discussion with at least eight individuals who reflect on their immigration or migration to the United States (US) and New York, New York. The narrators tend to speak over one another, making it difficult to distinguish who is speaking; some narrators contribute more to the conversation than others; and the volume fluctuates throughout the interview.
    Topics covered in this interview include reasons for immigration or migration; family situations both before and after immigration or migration; living conditions in New York City, especially during the Great Depression; race relations within the US; jobs and working conditions; the comparison between New York City neighborhoods in the past and at the time of the interview; and student riots over rising college tuition costs at the time of the interview. The interview ends with the unknown moderator addressing the logistics of individual interviews for those who are interested.
    See also: Accent, Sedrkk; Johns, Ponnie; Manar, [Unknown]; and Meeks, Danny.
  - Council Workshop for Senior Citizens II, 1973 March 27; 344224 (Box 73, Reel 216a - 216b)
    This group interview was conducted by student interviewers, Edmund Lake and Karin Young, and an unknown moderator at the Council Workshop for Senior Citizens on 125th Street in Manhattan, New York on March 27, 1973. This interview consists of a roundtable discussion with at least eight individuals, who all reflect on their immigration or migration to the United States (US) and New York, New York. The narrators tend to speak over one another, making it difficult to distinguish who is speaking, and some narrators contribute more to the conversation than others.
    Topics covered in this interview include reasons for immigration or migration; family situations before and after immigration or migration; living conditions in New York, New York; native New Yorkers' views of and relationships with the increasing immigrant population; race relations within the US; immigration journeys and conditions; jobs and working conditions; and the comparison between New York City neighborhoods in the past and at the time of the interview. The interview ends with the moderator addressing the logistics of individual interviews for those who are interested.